So, I want to talk a little bit about the arrangement
...that Demi Lovato used last night at the Super Bowl
...for her rendition of the American national anthem.
It very clearly was referencing
...Whitney Houston's 1991 rendition
of 'The Star-Spangled Banner'.
But for me, the arrangement itself,
...kind of, missed the mark,
...and I want to explain why.
I spent some time last night
transcribing the arrangement,
...and I thought it would be fun
for us to listen to it together,
...and me giving my thoughts on
...why I don't think it's quite as strong as John Clayton's
arrangement that he did for Whitney Houston.
So, let's check out the Demi Lovato.
All right, so right away,
...I'm pretty sure they're using MIDI with a
sample library instead of a real orchestra,
...which is not the end of the world,
...but it does add this cheese factor to the whole sound.
Also, the opening is fairly stark.
You have these two lines moving in contrary motion,
...but they start
...on a distance: this major 9th
...and this naked tritone right here
...resolve into a major 6th.
I might soften that dissonance by adding an inner line,
...which goes:
So it sounds like this:
That's a minor detail,
...but for me, it's indicative of
problems with the full arrangement,
...which doesn't feel as fleshed out as it could be.
Anyway, let's keep listening.
All right, right into the jazz chords.
The way that these are harmonized
...are with a triad in the upper places
...and the third in the bass,
...creating an inversion.
But the third in the upper voice is replaced
...by the second degree of the scale,
...creating, in this case:
And then, also:
This is a lot of harmonic richness up front,
...which is not necessarily a bad thing,
...because there's this warm and
regal quality to these chords.
By introducing this sort of harmonic language early on,
...it...
...I don't know, for me, creates expectations
that it will continue growing,
...and as we'll see, it doesn't really.
But anyway, let's keep listening.
All right, some nice stuff in there.
And even though there is some melismatic
reinterpretations of the melody,
...Demi Lovato keeps it fairly straight,
...which I do appreciate.
I guess, for me, in this section,
...there's a little bit of a, I guess,
...mismatch of the density of
harmony between two chords.
So if we have this
Csus4
...resolving to a C,
...it sounds a little strange to me
to go to the jazz chords,
...the D♭sus2/F immediately afterwards.
Especially
...when that chord resolves to a tonic major chord
...on 'twilight's last gleaming'.
There's something fairly weak about it.
I don't know,
...I don't believe it.
But anyway,
...let's keep listening.
Okay, one thing I want to mention here is that
...of the arrangement is a little strange.
None of the chords are landing with
Demi Lovato on the downbeats,
...and so it doesn't feel as grounded
as maybe it could be.
This is gonna be a little bit of a problem
for me later on in the arrangement,
...so I just wanted to mention it now.
Also, the arranger's preoccupation with this G♭13
...is kind of like a moment of harmonic surprise.
Or sometimes voiced as A♭ over G♭ later on.
It starts becoming a little-
...a little bit grating.
But anyway, let's keep going.
Like you heard that, right?
There's never an arrival on the downbeat,
...which is okay,
...but it gives the whole arrangement
this fairly weak feeling.
We never
...get there.
All right, so the harmony now seems to be getting
...simpler,
...which is strange to me because it started with all this
It's like the arranger changed their mind on the
harmonic scheme as they were going through,
...which is almost exactly the opposite
of John Clayton's arrangement
...that he did for Whitney Houston.
The harmonic idea on the word
'proof' in this arrangement
...is more or less the same as the idea in John
Clayton's arrangement for Whitney Houston.
But John Clayton gives us a spicy
chord on this climactic moment,
...and man, does it feel good.
Oh my god, it's so good.
OOH!
Mmph!
So good!
Ah, I feel so good when I hear it.
Ahhh
It's so good.
I love it.
I love it so much!
Man, the arrangement on Whitney Houston's version,
...there's just so much drama there
...and it matches the intensity.
Whereas
...on the Demi Lovato version,
...the intensity just is not there at the moment,
...even though
...Demi is giving a fairly
dramatic vocal performance.
Like, the F minor, there's no drama there.
You don't necessarily need to use spicy chords like:
You could, for example, give a low bass hit like:
Something to that effect, just...
...giving it more.
It's kind of strange to me, because
...there is a time and place for a reserved
arrangement of 'The Star-Spangled Banner'.
That's not what Demi Lovato is gonna give you,
...she's gonna give you her
Whitney Houston impression.
And as an arranger, you have to
...meet the challenge and...
That's not...
That's not that.
For me, the rest of the arrangement kind of
...peters out from here.
L- Let's keep listening.
Okay. While I do like
...that harmonic moment of the D7 to the
...E♭(sus4) to E♭,
...it doesn't really fit the whole vibe that
we've been constructing so far,
...but it is nice.
I do- I do concede that.
Anyway:
All right, this is where the MIDI kind of gets to me.
The reeds are very hot in the mix
...and they don't sound all that great.
It definitely sounds like a sample library.
I mean, maybe I'm wrong, but...
It's the Super Bowl.
We should have like a huge orchestra
...and we get like, "Hey...
"I worked on this in GarageBand."
But hey, whatever.
More power to you.
All right, I haven't talked about
Demi's singing all that much,
...but I do like the fact that she saved
some of the melisma for the word 'wave'.
It makes sense.
It's like a flag waving,
...you're going up and down with all the fancy notes.
It works for me.
I know some people really don't like
when singers embellish it that much,
...but this feels tasteful to me.
Okay, so...
One, why didn't we land on the downbeat there?
It feels fairly weak and...
...sparse but like not in a good way.
And alternatively,
...on the word 'free',
Why are we doing this, like, really quiet
...G♭13
...when she's going up to the high A♭ at
the top of the register and giving the
...ultimate climactic moment to the whole arrangement?
To me, it feels
...so counter on a philosophical
level to the vocal arrangement.
The story that this arrangement is
trying to tell has nothing to do
...with the vocal performance of Demi Lovato,
The vocal performance being so indebted to Whitney
Houston's version that it's impossible to pull them apart.
And part of what made Whitney
Houston's version so great
...was John Clayton's
...awesome, awesome arrangement.
So for me, this feels,
...I don't know,
...not good?
I don't mean to rag on this arranger so much,
...but I do want to explain why I
feel like this arrangement is weak.
Okay.
So at this moment on the word 'brave',
...we have these very delicate string pads
...resolving like this.
The problem is, of course,
...is that there are literal
...fighter jets flying up above
...and the crowd roaring the word 'brave'.
The arrangement has nothing
to do with the musical situation.
The classic Whitney Houston version,
of course, has the climactic
...going to
That kind of progression feels a
little bit cheesy and on the nose
...for me and most other musical situations.
But when fighter jets are flying,
...give me that ♭VI, ♭VII, I anywhere
...because it feels the most appropriate.
Now, there's other things that I have
problems with in the arrangement, like
...there should be more orchestral percussion, I think.
There should definitely be more snare drums
...people banging on snare drums and
...crashes and bass drums and all that stuff.
I mean, you can program that in MIDI libraries
...and it will definitely fill out the whole sound.
But I guess my main problem with this is...
There's a rich tradition
...of pops orchestral arranging.
Orchestrators and arrangers working on Broadway
...and Hollywood
...all over the place.
And there is definitely a canon of arranging
...that can be brought to something like
'The Star-Spangled Banner'
...at the Super Bowl.
To me, this arrangement was not of that caliber,
...and that's what's a little disappointing.
Now some people on Twitter were
...comparing it to my arrangements of pop songs, which
...to be fair, yeah.
There are a lot of jazz chords
and it might feel a little disjointed,
...but the number one thing that
I want to do when I'm creating
...a reharmonized and reimagined version of a pop song
...is I want to tell a story.
I want the story to make sense.
I want to have every choice, every musical choice
...lead to somewhere else.
This arrangement, I feel like it didn't really do that,
...so that's why I was a little bit disappointed with it.
Anyway,
...if you enjoy videos like this,
...please consider donating to my Patreon,
...because it's the patrons over at Patreon
that make this channel possible.
Thank you so much for watching,
And, uh...
Yeah.
Have a good one, everybody.